Guide to the Communications Workers of America, Local 1172 Records WAG.093
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America, Local 1172 Records
1953-1993
1960-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America. Local 1172
Champlin, Richard
WAG.093
4.25 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons and 1 folder.
Breakaway members of the American Communications Association organized Communications Workers of America, Local 1172 in 1954. Local 1172 initially represented employees of the American Cable and Radio Corporation east of the Mississippi. Later Local 1172 became part of CWA District 1, and expanded to represent employees of International Telephone and Telegraph (ITT) Worldwide Communications and Western Union, as well as radio operators employed by Air-India. In 1993, Local 1172 merged with CWA Local 1177. The Communications Workers of America, Local 1172 Records includes the Local's charter, bylaws and minutes of the executive board and membership meetings, bargaining files, agreements, correspondence, photographs, grievance reports and arbitration cases filed on behalf of the Local's members.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Richard Champlin, former president of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1172, in 1993. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1993.014 and 1993.015.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Communications Workers of America (CWA), Local 1172 had its origins in the American Communications Association (ACA), a CIO union that organized radio and telegraph operators. After the ACA was expelled from the CIO in 1950 on charges of Communist domination the CWA conducted an organizing campaign, which resulted in some ACA members breaking away to form CWA Local 1172. The Local was chartered in 1954, with Morton Bahr as its first president. From 1954 to 1967 the jurisdiction of the Local covered employees of the American Cable and Radio Corporation (AC&R) east of the Mississippi. In 1967 AC&R was taken over by ITT World Communications, despite CWA protests to the Federal Communications Commission, and the Local's jurisdiction was adjusted accordingly. In the 1970s the Local expanded to include radio operators employed by Air India. The takeover of ITT World Communications by Western Union in 1987 involved the Local in protracted struggles over layoffs, restructuring, outsourcing and the transfer of benefits. Having suffered a decline in membership, Local 1172 was merged with CWA, Local 1177 in 1993.
Scope and Content Note
The Communications Workers of America, Local 1172 Records includes the Local's charter, bylaws and minutes of the executive board and membership meetings, bargaining files, agreements, correspondence, photographs, grievance reports and arbitration cases filed on behalf of the Local's members.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 3 series:
Missing Title
I, Minutes
II, General Files
III, Grievances and Arbitration Cases
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America Records (WAG 124)
Communications Workers of America Records: Addendum (WAG 124.1)
Communications Workers of America, District 1 Records (WAG 117)
Fliers (printed matter); Financial records; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Correspondence.; Arbitration, Industrial.; Company unions -- Telecommunication.; Labor unions -- Officials and employees.; Discrimination in employment.; Legal documents.; Collective labor agreements -- Telecommunication.; Reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Clippings (information artifacts); Labor unions -- Political activity -- United States.; Labor unions -- Contract administration.; Strikes and lockouts -- Telecommunication.; Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- United States.; Telecommunication -- Employees -- United States.; Telecommunication -- United States -- History.; ITT Corporation; United States. National Labor Relations Board; Air-India; Communications Workers of America; Western Union Telegraph Company; Champlin, Richard
- Series I: Charters, Bylaws and Minutes, 1953-1992
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I: Charters, Bylaws and Minutes, includes the Local's Charter, Bylaws and Minutes of the Executive Board and Membership Meetings. These are organized chronologically within each type.
  - Charters and Jurisdiction, 1953-1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bylaws, 1968-1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes: Executive Board, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes: Membership Meetings, 1983-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: General Files, 1952-1993
  Series II: General Files, includes bargaining files of Air-India, ITT Worldwide Communication and Western Union; as well as agreements, photographs, and correspondence. These are organized alphabetically by topic.
  - Air India, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Air India Bargaining, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Cable and Radio Agreement (Photocopy-original in box 4), 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Attendance and Lateness, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bargaining, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining, Apr 1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining, May 1, 1963-May 15, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining, May 16, 1963-May 31, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bargaining, Jun 1963-Jul 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Budgets, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Local President, 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Local Secretary-Treasurer, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Federal Communications Commission (FCC), 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - FCC, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - FCC, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Health and Safety, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - International Telephone and Telegraph (ITT) Worldwide Communications, 1953-1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - ITT/ACR, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - ITT Agreements, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - ITT Bargaining, May 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - ITT Bargaining, Jun 1965-Jul 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - ITT Bargaining, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - ITT Bargaining, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - ITT Bargaining, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Layoffs, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Layoffs, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Local Officers, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Membership, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) Cases, 1952-1983 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters (Local 1172 News), 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New York Downstate CWA Council, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Outsourcing, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Outsourcing, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Pensions-General, 1982-1991 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, 1988, undated (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 1)
  - Strike, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Strike Manual (CWA), 1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Suspensions, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Terminations, 1979-1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Warning Letters, 1982-1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Western Union, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Western Union, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Western Union Bargaining, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Whippany, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - World Communications, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - World Communications, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - World Communications, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - World Communications Agreements, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - World Communications Agreements, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Series III: Grievances and Arbitration Cases, 1956-1992
  Series III: Grievances and Arbitration Cases, includes grievance reports and arbitration cases filed on behalf of the Local's members. The grievances are organized alphabetically by the member's last name, and the arbitration cases are organized by the case number.
  - Grievances: Miscellaneous, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Barnes, Audruban, 1982-1987 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bennett, Nellie, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Contessa, Douglas, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Corvino, William, 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dawson, Calvin, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Downing, William Jr., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Estrema, Louis, 1983-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Filleccia, Thomas, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Innes, Michael, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Jacobs, Lou, 1982-1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Marin, William, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - McHugh, Jim, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - McKeough, Thomas, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - O'Brien, Lorraine, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pavlu, Ed, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Perez, Nelson, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sheekey, Thomas, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Scordato, Robert, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Simon, Leslie, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Sonego, Vincent, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Swann, Geraldine, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Tonnesen, Leiv, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Grievance Reports NYO 23-NYO 2198, undated (Box 3, Folder 24-115)
  - Grievance Reports NYO 2202-NYO 2354, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-37)
  - Grievance Reports NYC 1-NYC 142, undated (Box 4, Folder 38-42)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0026-78, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0035-84, 1958, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0137-78, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0399-82, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0412-87, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0692-82, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-0849-86, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-1035-77, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Arbitration Case 1330-1354-83, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - American Cable and Radio (original), 1956 (Box 4, Folder 52)